<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The arraignment of the Arrian. His beginning. height. fall In a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, Iune 4. 1624. Being the first Sunday in Trinitie terme. By Humphry Sydenham Mr. of Arts, and fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13262</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23559</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101838</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837641</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837641</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1978</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13262)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1978)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1396:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The arraignment of the Arrian. His beginning. height. fall In a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, Iune 4. 1624. Being the first Sunday in Trinitie terme. By Humphry Sydenham Mr. of Arts, and fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Eliot's Court Press] for Iohn Parker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also issued as part of his "Five sermons, upon severall occasions", STC 23563.</note>
                  <note>Printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Central Library (Bristol, Eng.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1978:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ARRAIGNMENT OF THE ARRIAN. His
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Beginning.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Height.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fall.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> In a Sermon preached at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe, <hi>Iune</hi> 4. 1624. Being the firſt Sunday in <hi>Trinitie</hi> Terme.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Humphry Sydenham</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> of <hi>Arts,</hi> and Fellow of WADHAM <hi>Colledge</hi> in OXFORD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for IOHN PARKER. 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1978:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1978:2"/>
            <head>TO MY APPROVED WORTHY FRIEND M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Francis Croſsing;</hi> This.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was neuer yet ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous in my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, as to value the worth of him I ſerue, by the title, but the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition; He is <hi>noble</hi> to me, that is ſo in his <hi>actions,</hi> not his <hi>deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent;</hi> thoſe high-ſwolne priuiledges of <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>fortune</hi> are (for the moſt part) <hi>tympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> in <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> pricke them, and they proue
<pb facs="tcp:1978:3"/> windes of <hi>honour,</hi> not ſubſtances. Had I beene ambitious of a high <hi>Patronage,</hi> this weake peece I ſend you might haue worne an <hi>honourable</hi> inſcription, but I haue that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me which chides thoſe inſolencies, and tells me that the name of <hi>friend</hi> ſounds better than of <hi>Lord,</hi> and hee is leſſe mine that doth onely <hi>countenance</hi> me, than he that <hi>feeds</hi> me; He onely deſerues to be a protector of my Labours which hath beene a cheriſher of my fortunes; to you then this at once flies for Patronage, and acceptance, deſiring you to receiue it as a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of his thankfulneſſe, who euer deuotes himſelfe</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt-moſt reſpectiue HVM: SYDENHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1978:3"/>
            <head>THE ARAIGNMENT OF THE ARRIAN.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>IOHN 8.58.</bibl>
                  <p>Before Abraham was, I am.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Euer age afforded a perfection of that eminencie which was not expoſed to enuie, or oppoſition, or both. Truth is the childe of vertue; and, as the inheritreſſe of all her glories; ſo, her ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings. Now, vertue growes by vniuſt wounds, &amp; ſo doth truth too; and like ſteele that is bent, ſpringeth the other way. She ſhewes her beſt luſtre vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on encounter, and like the Sunne ſhines brighteſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two clowds, <hi>malice, errour;</hi> both (here) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire to ouercaſt and darken the glory of thoſe beames which enlighten euery man that comes into the world,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1978:4"/> 
               <hi>the ſunnes of righteouſneſſe.</hi> It hath euer beene the ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem and proiect of that <hi>Arch-enemy</hi> of man, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement and ſtrengthening of his great title — <hi>The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lies</hi> —, either to ſtrangle truth in the conception, or ſmother it in the birth. If he miſcarry in his owne particular vndertakings, hee will ſuborne his Factors, <hi>Scrives</hi> and <hi>Phariſees;</hi> and theſe not onely to queſtion, but to oppoſe a deity, fit agents put vpon ſuch a damned deſigne, for it is theirs no leſſe by debt, than parentage; — <hi>Ye are of your Father the Deuill, v.</hi> 44. He hath bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed you a prodigious lie, and you would faine practiſe it on the Sauiour of the world, labouring to nullifie his acts, blemiſh his deſcent, impoſture all his miracles. Where were they euer ſeconded, but by the finger of a God? or, where contradicted, but by the malice of a Iew? could the powers of the graue, and the ſhackles and bands of death be diſſolued, and broken by the meere hand of <hi>Beelzebub?</hi> or a dead and ſtinking carkaſſe, enliued and quickened by a <hi>Samaritan and his deuill?</hi> could the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darkneſſe, and all thoſe legions below, fetch a ſoule out of the boſome of your <hi>Abraham,</hi> and re-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne it in a body foure daies entombed? no, that — <hi>Magnus hiatus interte, &amp; nos</hi> —, returnes the lie vpon all helliſh power, and the prince thereof. — <hi>Between: you, and vs, there is a great gulfe fixed, Luke</hi> 16.26. Why then exclaime you on the iniuſtice and falſhood of his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies? <hi>Opera quae ego facio —, the workes which I doe beare witneſſe of me.</hi> Looke on them, and if they vnſcale not your wilfull blindneſſe, the axioms and principles of your owne law will conuince you. It is written in your <hi>Thalmud, — That the teſtimony of two men is true</hi> —. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold then out of your own bloud, and Nation, two ſtrong euidences againſt you, Iewes both, and both ſpeake him a true God, — <hi>A virgin ſhall conceiue and bring forth a Sonne, and his name ſhall be called Emmanuell, God with vs,</hi> Iſa. 7.14. <hi>This is our God, and there ſhall be none in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1978:4"/> compariſon of him, Baruch</hi> 3.36. Why then are ye ſo ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at his naming <hi>Abraham?</hi> or why doth your indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſwell, that he ſaies he is before him? <hi>Abraham reioyced to ſee my day, and ſaw it, and was glad, verſ.</hi> 56. (My day of eternity, and my day of incarnation, with the eie of faith.) Why enquire you into the number of his yeeres? a whole age to him is as an houre, two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeeres but as a minute, and all the wheeles and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of time within his ſpan, and as a <hi>nunc</hi> or inſtant; before <hi>Abraham</hi> was, before the world, before all time <hi>I am. Iew,</hi> take his word, it is orthodox, or if not, his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeueration: and if that be too ſlight and ſingle, loe, hee doubles it, <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay vnto you, before Abraham was, I am.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now thou that ſitteſt in the chaire of <hi>Moſes,</hi> heare what S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tells thee, — <hi>Appende verba, &amp; cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſce myſterium</hi> —, the words (indeed) are of a narrow circuit, yet they ſhrine and inuolue a myſtery, and carry with them both maieſty and depth, like rich ſtones ſet in Ebonie, where though the ground be darke, yet it giues their luſtre and beauty clearer; learne here then both propriety, and weight of language, and how to criticke between a God, and thy owne frailty. — <hi>Intellige, fieret, ad humanam facturam, ſum verò, ad diuinam pertinere ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiam? — Was,</hi> points onely to a humane conſtitution, — <hi>I am,</hi> to a diuine ſubſtance, and therefore the originall hath a — <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> — for <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp; an — <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> — for <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Diuinity is not cloiſtered or confined to time, either paſt, or future, but commands all as preſent; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not — <hi>I was,</hi> but — <hi>I am.</hi> Neither doe the Latines giue <hi>Abraham</hi> an — <hi>eſſet,</hi> but a — <hi>fieret,</hi> nor <hi>Chriſt</hi> a — <hi>fui,</hi> but a — <hi>ſum.</hi> Hereupon the full tide of Expoſitors, beſides <note n="*" place="margin">Ego latius ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo, Cal. in 8. lo.</note> M. <hi>Caluine,</hi> and his <hi>Marlorate,</hi> (who though they a while diuide the ſtreame, yet at length they meet in the ſame channell, and ſo make the current a little ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler) waue this way, and ſend vs to that — <hi>I am,</hi> of <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:1978:5"/> in the 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 14. <hi>verſ.</hi> where wee finde the roote with an — <hi>Ehich, Aſher Ehich,</hi> which though the Chaldee renders, — <hi>Ero qui ero, I will be that I will be</hi> — (which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is the genuine ſignification of the originall) yet the vulgar Edition giues it in the preſent, — <hi>I am that I am</hi> — and the <hi>Septuagint</hi> — <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, — <hi>I am he that is</hi> — (it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both frequent and neceſſary with the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> to place the future for the preſent) and by this they imply — <hi>Gods eternall and vnchangeable being in himſelfe.</hi> The <hi>Thalmudiſts</hi> alſo (whoſe authority muſt paſſe for current, where there is no power to contradict, or ſcanne) allow this, — <hi>Ehich</hi> — as much as — <hi>Sam — Fiſi — ero</hi> — the compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of three times, <hi>paſt, preſent,</hi> and <hi>to come</hi> —. So the <hi>Rabbins</hi> in <hi>Elleſhemoth Rabbi</hi> vpon this Text, reade, — <hi>I that haue beene,</hi> and <hi>I the ſame now,</hi> and <hi>I the ſame for time to come.</hi> Howeuer the <hi>Chaldee Paraphraſt</hi> labours an indifferency, and hath charity enough to afford both interpretations, — <hi>He that was, and hereafter will be. — Ad denotandam aeternitatem eius</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ionathan</hi>) to ſhew the eternall being of him who alone can ſay — <hi>Sam, ero — I am, and I will be;</hi> for he is the very ſource and fountaine of all life and eſſence, <hi>In whom we liue, and moue, and haue our being</hi> —, and by reaſon of this triplicity of time, and power, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>atablus</hi> would deriue <hi>Ihehouah</hi> from this word — <hi>Ehich</hi> (though ſome of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors fetch the pedigree a little higher) from — <hi>Hauah, — He was,</hi> and tels vs that by the firſt letter is ſignified, <hi>he wil be,</hi> and by the ſecond — <hi>Ho, — He is;</hi> &amp; to this <hi>Rabbi Bechai</hi> ſeems to aſſent, in his 65. <hi>page</hi> vpon <hi>Exodus.</hi> But howeuer they war a little in the deriuation, they do not in the ſubſtance, proportioning both this triple priuiledg, &amp; where there is ſuch an immenſity, we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but make a God, &amp; where ſuch a God, eternitie. All things beſides him once were not, and being, are limited in their natures, neither could poſſibly perſiſt, vnleſſe God preſerued them; many alſo haue loſt or ſhall looſe their proper eſſence, and whilſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1978:5"/> they remaine are obnoxious to daily fluctuarions; only God eternally — <hi>Is</hi> — without beginning, limitation, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance, mutation, end, conſiſting onely of himſelfe, and all other creatures of him, and therefore this — <hi>Ehich — I am</hi> — is a peculiar attribute of omnipotencie, not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining any other, but indeterminatlie ſignifying all manners of being, for ſo it imports — <hi>The very immenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Gods ſubſtance,</hi> — and to this with an vnanimous conſent all interpreters ſubſcribe, and the whole quire of Fathers. I haue now brought — <hi>Ehich</hi> — cloſe up with <hi>Iehouah,</hi> this — <hi>I am</hi> — with him that is — <hi>Firſt</hi> — and <hi>Laſt,</hi> ſo that we may here rather challenge than borrow that of the <hi>Apoſtle; Ieſus Chriſt yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever.</hi> Where <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> will put <hi>Chriſt</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that triple prerogatiue to make him a compleat God, too. — <hi>A yeſterday,</hi> for time paſt, — <hi>to day</hi> — preſent — <hi>for euer,</hi> to come, though I meet here (as I ſhall in euery cranny and paſſage of my diſcourſe) a violent oppoſer, <hi>Eniedinus Samoſatenianus,</hi> who limits the <hi>Apoſtles — Heri</hi> — and <hi>Hodie — ad Rem nuperam, &amp; recentem</hi> —, ſo in <hi>Iob</hi> (he ſaies) men are called — <hi>Heſterni</hi> — by the <hi>Greekes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> — <hi>yeſterday</hi> — and <hi>to day</hi> — for their breuitie of life; but this interpretation is no leſſe bold than deſperate, and that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> — which followes in the originall, will cut off all comment and gloſſe of tranſitorineſſe — <hi>The ſame for euer</hi> — and therefore we find him cloathed with peculiar titles of the Almighty, and by Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> foure ſeuerall times fronted with an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, — <hi>from him that was, and is, and is to come;</hi> — ſo that if any murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vnbeleeuer ſhould recoile in the acknowledgement of Chriſts diuinitie, he beats on againe, a third &amp; a fourth time, that if he can not pierce the ſtonie heart by a ſingle perſwaſion, he will batter it by inculcation. Howeuer the malice or peruerſeneſſe of moſt ages haue brought this truth not onely vpon termes of ſcruple, but oppoſition, ſo that now it is growne diſputable, whether Chriſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1978:6"/> more in his body by the fury and violence of the hand, or in his diuinitie by the ſcourge and ſting of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous and deprauing tongues? one would haue him, <hi>no God,</hi> another <hi>no man;</hi> this againe would haue him <hi>a meere man,</hi> and that denies him <hi>a true bodie;</hi> one ſtrips him quite of <hi>fleſh,</hi> another cloathes him with it, but makes it <hi>ſinfull;</hi> this would haue him an <hi>Angell,</hi> that little better than a <hi>deuill,</hi> or at leaſt that <hi>he vſed one.</hi> One, <hi>no bodie,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (I beleeue) <hi>nothing — Eſt illud mirabile</hi> (ſaith <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi>) <hi>Cum omnes haereſes inuicem pugnent; in falſitate omnes conſentire</hi> —.</p>
            <p>Euery head is frantike with a ſtrange opinion, and that with ſome wilde fancie, which all meet in the ſame im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probabilitie and (which it euer breeds) falſhood. Errour and infidelitie may blow on diuine truth, and ſhake it too, but not ouerthrow it; 'tis founded on ſuch a Baſis and ſure ground-worke as is ſubiect neither to battery nor vndermining. <hi>The Rocke, Chriſt.</hi> The <hi>Iew</hi> and the <hi>Arrian</hi> lay on fiercely here, not onely to deface this goodly ſtructure, but to demoliſh it, and ruine (if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) his diuinitie; but lend me a while your noble atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Ile ſhew you with what weakneſſe they come off, what diſhonour. In the trauerſing of which giue mee leaue to make vſe of that Apologie which in the ſame ſubject Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> did to <hi>Gratian, — Nolo argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to credas (ſancte Imperator<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) &amp; noſtrae diſputationi; ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turas interrogemus, interrogemus Apoſtolos, Prophetas, Chriſtum.</hi> Leane not ſo much to my ſtrength of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and diſputation, as to a ſacred authoritie &amp; proofe, Let vs aske the Scriptures, Patriarchs, Prophets, Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, Apoſtles, Chriſt; let me adde (for ſo both my taske and induſtrie require) Fathers, Councels, Rabbins, Schoolemen, Hiſtories ſacred and prophane, let's giue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie her due, and not in a lazy thirſt drinke of the ſtreame, (which is either troubled or corrupt) when wee may haue our fill at a cleere fountaine; to traffique here
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1978:6"/> at home with a few moderne Syſteames, is no ſmall ſinne of the age onely, but our profeſſion too, if we can fleyle downe the tranſgreſſions of the time in ſome few ſtolne <hi>Poſtelliſmus,</hi> and peece a ſacred line with a worme-eaten Apophthegme, ſo it be done in a frequent and haſty zeale, we are the Sages and the Patriots of the time, and the lights no doubt of this vnder firmament; but our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe grouels not ſo low; we are here to tread a maze, and threed a Labyrinth, ſometimes on hils of ice, where, if we ſlip in the leaſt <hi>punctum,</hi> we tumble into haereſio; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with <hi>Peter</hi> in the deepe, that if the hand of <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not a little ſuccour vs, we ſhould ſinke into infidelity. I will ball aſſe my diſcourſe with as much cautelouſneſſe as I may, and where I meet with difficulties which are ſtony and vntrodden, if I cannot fairely maſter them, I will oppoſe them with my beſt ſtrength, and if not finde a way ſmooth to ſatisfaction, dig on; I may perchance awaken haereſies, but I will lull them againe in their own ſlumber, I will onely pull aſide the vaile and ſhew you their vglineſſe, and ſhut them vp in their owne deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. I know I am to ſpeake to an Auchtorie, as well ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with faith, as vnderſtanding, and yet (perchance) not without ſome mixture and touch of weakneſſe. Here are ſhallowes then for Lambes to wade, and deepes for Elephants to ſwimme, paſſages which he leuell with humble capacities; others which will venture to ſtand vp with riper iudgments, if they ſtoop ſomtimes and ſeeme too low for theſe, and mount againe and proue too high for others, it was euer my deſire to keepe a correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the beſt, and ſo to make vſe of that of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, — Non fraudabo eos qui poſſunt capere, dum timeo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluus eſſe auribus corum qui non poſſunt capere</hi> —. Yet come I not to fill thoſe eares which are pickt and dreſt for accurateneſſe I am ſo farre from labouring to pleaſe ſuch, that I intend to vex them; if any charitable care bee prone to a ſoure diſcourſe, pitch that attention heere one
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1978:7"/> houre, and I ſhall make good my promiſe out of the words of the Text.
<q>Before Abraham was, I am.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And here we are firſt to enter lifts with that capitall and Arch-enemy of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the vexation of the Fathers, and the incendiary and firebrand of the Eaſtern Church, the <hi>Arrian,</hi> who out of an enuious pride is at once boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and iniurious, willing to inueſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> with the title <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but diſrobes him of that glorious, and his owne <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, granting him a <hi>like</hi> eſſence with the Father not the <hi>ſame:</hi> equall to him in <hi>power,</hi> not <hi>eternitie;</hi> but giue me leaue to ſtrip one heriticke to cloath another, and put on ours what <hi>Tertullian</hi> did on <hi>Marcion — Quid di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>idias mendacio Chriſtum?</hi> why doſt thou thus peece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meale and mince a deity, and <hi>halfe god</hi> (as it were) the Son of the Almighty? — <hi>Totus veritas,</hi> he is the ſpirit of truth, and oracle of his Father, <hi>the brightneſſe of his glory,</hi> in whom are hid all the treaſures of <hi>Wiſedome, knowledge,</hi> by whom God made the world.</p>
            <p>It were too bold a ſoleciſme to ranke tranſitorineſſe with what is ſacred, or that which is fleeting with euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingneſſe, what below eternall dare we make compati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with omnipotencie?</p>
            <p>An eternall Intellect, moſt perfect, and ſuch is God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires an obiect equally perfect, and eternall, which from God, holding a relation to God, can be nothing but God it ſelfe; and ſeeing that no Intellect can conceiue without the image of that obiect which it conceiues, it will follow of neceſſitie that God, ſince from all eternitie he knew himſelfe moſt perfect, ſhould conceiue and bring forth in himſelfe a moſt perfect image of himſelfe, his Sonne. There is no act of vnderſtanding without imagination, which naturally preſents an <hi>image,</hi> by ſo much the more perfect, by how much the obiect, whoſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1978:7"/> image it is, is more diuinely excellent. And this is that the Apoſtle glanc't at, when he ſtiled <hi>Chriſt, — Characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem hypoſtaſis patris</hi> — the expreſſe <hi>image</hi> of his Fathers perſon, a ſonne ſo begotten <hi>of</hi> and <hi>in</hi> the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the Father, that there can be nothing from it, diuers, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugning. Seeing then, in God to <hi>vnderſtand</hi> and <hi>to be</hi> are not ſo much parallels, as equals. <hi>Intelligi autem ſit ipſum filij eſſe</hi> — as the Schoole ſpeakes — <note place="margin">Keck. Syſt. Theol. l. 1. ca. 2.</note> ſtrength of conſequence will induce, that the ſubſtance of Father and Sonne, ſound one both in power and euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; in fine, for as much as the <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> of God is from eternitie, actiue, nay, the very act eternall, and that <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> cannot be without an <hi>Image,</hi> It followes that this <hi>Image</hi> which was conceiued, the Sonne, was equall to that which did conceiue, the Father, ſo that the eternitie of God the Sonne, and his equalitie with God the Father doth ariſe from that eſſentiall Identitie of both, for where two perſons ſhall agree in the ſame eſſence, if the one be infinite, the other muſt riuall in the ſame eternitie.</p>
            <p>Here is the Rock then on which we build our Church, and the ſure <hi>Baſis</hi> where we foot and faſten our beleefe. — <hi>The Sonne is begotten of the eſſence of the Father, and alwayes begotten, — Non quòd quotidiè renouetur illa gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio, ſed quia ſemper eſt,</hi> — ſaith <hi>Origen,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tom. 2. hom. 6. in Ierem.</note> not becauſe it is dailie renouated, but becauſe it euer — <hi>Is</hi> — or rather — <hi>Was.</hi> For Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> in the 29 of his <hi>Morals,</hi> the firſt Chapter, plaies as well the <hi>Criticke,</hi> as the Diuine, and is no leſſe nice, than ſolid, — <hi>Dominus neſter Ieſus Chriſt us in eo quòd virtus &amp; ſapientia Dei eſt, de patre ante tempora natus eſt, vel potius quia nec coepit naſci, nec deſift dicam verius, ſemper</hi> natus, <hi>non poſſumus, ſemper</hi> naſcitur, <hi>nè im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectus eſſe videatur</hi> — Our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> in that he is the power and wiſedome of God is ſaid to be borne of the Father before all times, or rather becauſe there was no <hi>beginning</hi> or <hi>end</hi> of his generation, we may ſpeake more
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1978:8"/> congruouſly, he <hi>was</hi> alwayes borne, not — <hi>Is</hi> —, for that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſes ſome imperfection, and as the ſame Father pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecutes. <note place="margin">Vt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignari <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; perfectus, &amp; ſemper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; natus, quate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, &amp; natus ad perf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctionem pert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; ſemper ad aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>atem.</note> That we may declare him both perfect and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, we allow him as well a — <hi>ſemper</hi> — as a — <hi>Natus</hi> — for as much as — <hi>Natus</hi> — hath reference to perfection, — <hi>ſemper</hi> —, to eternitie. Howeuer S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his expoſition of that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, — Ego hodie genui te — Thou art my Son, this day haue I begotten thee, Pſal.</hi> 2. ſayes that — <hi>Hodiè — praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ſignificat</hi> and in eternitie, neither is the time paſt any thing, as if it ſhould ceaſe to be, nor time to come, as if it were not yet, but onely the time preſent, Becauſe whatſoeuer is eternall alwaies — <hi>Is</hi> — yet at length hee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands that place — <hi>de ſempiterna generatione ſapientiae D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i</hi> — And <hi>Lombard</hi> deſcants on it in his firſt booke ninth diſtinction, who would haue the Prophet to ſay — Genui — <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> putaretur,</hi> — hodiè — <hi>ne praeterita genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio videretur: I haue begotten thee,</hi> leſt it ſhould be thought new, <hi>to day,</hi> paſt, and thence out of the authoritie of the Text or the interpretation concludes a perpetuall gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Sonne from the eſſence of the Father.</p>
            <p>But here the Hereticke interpoſes, and thus ſubtilly beates at the gates of reaſon. <hi>A thing that is borre, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid that it was ouer, for in this reſpect it is ſaid to bee borne, that it might be. S. Hillarie,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 12. de Trin.</note> by a modeſt anſwer or confutation rather, limits his propoſition to things meerely ſecular, which borne here in the courſe of nature, muſt neceſſarily call on time, and tell vs they ſometimes were not, it is one thing then to be borne of that which alwayes <hi>is not,</hi> another of that which alwayes <hi>was,</hi> for that is temporary, this eternall.</p>
            <p>If then it be proper to God the Father, alwayes to be Father, it muſt be to God the Sonne, alwaies to be Sonne, ſo the Euangeliſt. <note place="margin">Ioh. 1. v. 1.</note> — <hi>In the beginning</hi> was <hi>the word, and the word</hi> was <hi>with God, and that word</hi> was <hi>God, and the ſame</hi> was <hi>from the beginning; erat, erat, erat, erat, en quater erat, vbi impius inuenit quod non erat?</hi> Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1978:8"/> his firſt to <hi>Gratian</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> &amp; indeed it was not without a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie when in that glorious transfiguration on Mount <hi>Tabor, Peter</hi> ſaw <hi>Chriſt</hi> with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> (<hi>when his face did ſhine as the Sunne, and his raiment was white as Snow</hi>) what did that viſion portend? <note place="margin">Ambroſ. vt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> 
               <hi>Niſi vt appareret nobis quod lex &amp; Prophetae cum Euangelio congruentes ſempiternum dei filium quem annunciauerant, reuelarent. But that it ſhould appeare vnto vs that the Law and the Goſpell going hand in hand with Euangelicall truth</hi> (for vnder <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo ſhrines thoſe three) <note place="margin">Aug. in orat. ad Catech. cap. 6.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould reveale vnto vs the euerlaſting Sonne of God, whom they had both foretold and ſhowne.</hi> And loe yet, as if theſe were not Oracles loude enough for the promulgation of ſuch a Maieſtie, the voice of the Almightie fils it vp with a — <hi>Hic eſt meus Dilectiſſimus — This is my beloued Sonne,</hi> My Sonne of eternitie, — <hi>Ego ex vtero ante Luciferum genui te —. Pſal.</hi> 34. And a ſonne of mine owne ſubſtance, — <hi>Ex ore Altiſſimi prodiui — Wiſ.</hi> 7. — <hi>primogenitus — before the day was, I am he, Eſay</hi> 43.13. — <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nigenitus — A iuſt God, and a Sauiour, There is none beſide me, Eſay</hi> 45.21. A Sonne begotten, not created, not of grace, but nature, <hi>before,</hi> not <hi>in</hi> time.</p>
            <p>Hereupon <hi>Chriſt</hi> taking his farewell of his Diſciples, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20. ſhewes them this <hi>Interuallum</hi> and diſtance of generation and adoption: <hi>I goe to my Father, and your Father, and to my God and your,</hi> not to <hi>our</hi> Father, but to <hi>mine</hi> and <hi>yours.</hi> This ſeparation implies a diuerſitie, and ſhewes that God is his <hi>Father</hi> indeed, but our <hi>Creator;</hi> and therefore he addes. <hi>My God and your God; Mine</hi> by a priuiledge of <hi>nature, yours</hi> of <hi>grace; Mine</hi> out of the wombe (as it were) of <hi>euerlaſtingneſſe; yours</hi> out of the iawes of <hi>time.</hi> Yet the <hi>Heretique</hi> would faine ſell vs to vnbeleefe and errour, by cheating <hi>Chriſt</hi> of an eternall birth-right, toſſing it on the tides of time, and ſo make him a creature, and no God.</p>
            <p>Heere to diſſent meerely were both perfunctory and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1978:9"/> dull, ſuch a falſhood merits rather defiance, than deniall, <note place="margin">Amb. vt ſupra.</note> — <hi>Negamus? potius horremus vacem</hi> —. Errours that are ſo inſolent are to be explos't, not diſputed, and ſpit at rather than contrould. Confutation ſwayes not heere, but violence, and therefore the Apoſtle driues this blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy to the head, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.15. Where we finde <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſtiled <hi>primogenitus vniuerſae Creaturae. The firſt-borne of euery creature;</hi> not the firſt <hi>created, — Vt genitus pro Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura, &amp; primus pro perpetuitate credatur</hi> —. ſaith <hi>Ambroſe; borne</hi> preſuppoſes diuine nature — <hi>Firſt,</hi> perpetuitie, and therefore when the pen of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſets him out in his full glory, he giues him this title <note place="margin">Col. 1.</note> — <hi>haeredem om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium —, — The heire of all things, by whom God made the world</hi> —, To make the world, and to be made in it, how contradictory? <note place="margin">Amb. 1. de ſi. ad Grat. cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Quis Authorem inter opera ſua deputet vt videatur eſſe quod fecit?</hi> ſaith the Father. Was there euer malice ſo ſhod with ignorance, which could not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the Artificer from his worke, the Potter from his clay, the Creator from the thing created? heare him ſpeak in whoſe mouth there was no guile. — <hi>Ego &amp; pater vnum ſumus, Ioh.</hi> 10. <hi>I and the Father are one. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num</hi> — to ſhew a conſent both of <hi>power</hi> and <hi>eternitie. — Sumus</hi> — a <hi>perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of nature without <hi>confuſion.</hi> Againe, — <hi>Vnum ſumus</hi> — not — <hi>vnus ſum</hi> — (ſo <hi>Auguſtine</hi> deſcants) <note place="margin">Orat. ad Catech. cap. 5.</note> — <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num</hi> — to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the <hi>Arrian, — Sumus</hi> — the <hi>Sabellian,</hi> the one diſioint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſeuering the times of Sonne and Father, the other confounding their perſons. — <hi>Vnum</hi> — than, to ſhew their eſſence <hi>one, — Sumus</hi> — the perſons <hi>diuers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could wiſh that we were now at truce, but with theſe there is neither peace nor ſafety, but in victory; wee are ſtill in the Front and violence of our Aduerſary, who puts on here as <hi>Philip</hi> did to <hi>Christ,</hi> with a — <hi>Domine oſtende nobis — Lord ſhew vs the Father, and it ſufficeth vs,</hi> but obſerue how the Lord replies, and in his reply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troules, and in his controulement cure's? <hi>Haue I been ſo long time with thee, and haſt thou not knowne me Philip?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1978:9"/> I came to reconcile thee to the Father, and wilt thou ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate me? Why ſeekeſt thou another? he that hath ſeene me, hath ſeene my Father alſo — Audi Arriane quid Dominus?</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>ſi erraſti cum Apoſtolo, redi cum Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Hearke <hi>Arrius</hi> how the Lord rebukes him, and if thou haſt digreſt with an Apoſtle, returne with an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, ſo his checke ſhall be thy conuerſion. But whilſt we thus ſhoulder with the <hi>Arrian,</hi> the <hi>Sabellian</hi> lies in am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh, who now comes on like lightning and thunder, but goes off like ſmoake; for looking backe to thoſe words of our Sauiour, he runnes on boldly to his owne paradox, and by this harmony of <hi>Sonne</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> would perſwade vs to a <hi>confuſion</hi> of their perſons; but the Text beares it not, and one little particle ſhall redeeme it from ſuch a prepoſterous interpretation; for it runnes not with a — <hi>Qui me videt, videt patrem, — He that ſees me, ſees my father,</hi> as if I were both father and ſonne, but with a — <hi>Qui me videt, videt — &amp; — patrem, — He that ſees me, ſees my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> alſo. <hi>Vbi interpoſitio vnius ſillabae,</hi> &amp;, <hi>patrem deſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit, &amp; filium, teque demonſtrat, neque patrem habere, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que filium, Auguſt.</hi> in his <hi>contra</hi> 5. <hi>hoſt. genera cap.</hi> 6. It is a rare opinion that hath not ſomething to hearten it either in truth or probability, otherwiſe it were no leſſe erroneous, than deſperate. But here there can be no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour or pretence for either, where both Diuinity and Arts breathe their defiance; that two natures ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue into one perſon, religion contradicts; two perſons into one nature, reaſon; but two perſons into one perſon, both reaſon &amp; religion. — <hi>Dixit Dominus Domino meo</hi> — ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>The Lord ſaid vnto my Lord, ſit at my right hand.</hi> Harke <hi>Sabellius,</hi> here is a <hi>Lord</hi> and a <hi>Lord</hi> two then, not one; where is now thy confuſion of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons? <hi>Ego Deus ſolus, &amp; non alius extra me, Deut.</hi> 32.12. <hi>I am God, and there is none beſide me —. Arrius</hi> where is thy God of <hi>eternity,</hi> and thy God of <hi>power,</hi> thy God of <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>operation,</hi> and thy God from the <hi>beginning?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1978:10"/> Audi Iſrael, Dominus noſter Deus vnus —, The Lord our God is God onely,</hi> no riuall, no ſharer in his omnipotency, for if temporary, how a God? if a God, how not eternall? if eternall, how not one? Thou alloweſt him the <hi>power</hi> of God, but not the <hi>eternity,</hi> the <hi>operation,</hi> not the <hi>time;</hi> what prodigy of errour? what dearth of reaſon? what warre of contradiction? what is this but to be God, and no God? temporary, and yet euerlaſting? Opinion once ſeeded in errour, ſhoots-out into hereſie, and after ſome growth of time, blaſphemy. Who (beſides an <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>) could haue thus molded two Gods out of one? ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept a <hi>Tritheite,</hi> or a <hi>Maniche?</hi> Who (ſcarce ſo groſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neither) denie them not an equality of <hi>time,</hi> but <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> coeternall, but this <hi>good,</hi> and that <hi>euill.</hi> Thus men ouer-borne with the ſtrength of a ſelfe-conceit, are ſo precipitated and drawne on with the ſwindge of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly fancy, that leauing the road and vſuall wayes of truth, they run into by-paths of errour, and ſo at length looſe both their iudgement, and their faith. Some haue beene ſo buſie with ſtarres, that they haue forgotten him that giues them influence; and like curious Lapida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, dally ſo long with ſparkling obiects, that they looſe the light of that organ which giues life vnto their Art. Learning (indeed) in many is a diſeaſe, not a perfection, a meere ſurfeit, rather vomited, than emptied, nothing paſſeth but what is forced, and as ſometimes with a fit of weakneſſe, ſo of pitty. A greedy knowledge feeds not our vnderſtanding, but oppreſſeth it, and like a rauenous appetite chewes more to poiſon, than to nouriſhment. Were I to drinke freely of what is ſacred, I ſhould deſire that which flowes, not that which is pumped for, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that are troubled yeeld mud, and are oftentimes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well the bane of the receiuer, as the comfort. A Pioner or bold myner which digs on too farre for his rich veine of Ore, meets with a dampe which choakes him; and we may finde ſome diſpoſitions rather deſperate than ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1978:10"/> knowne more by a heady reſolution, than a wiſe cautelouſneſſe, whom we may reſemble to that ſilly and ſtorme-toſt Seaman, who diued ſo long for a piece of his ſhipwrackt treaſure, that either want of aire, or ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſſe of water depriued him at once of life and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. <hi>Arrius</hi> hath been ſo long conuerſant in the ſchoole of Philoſophy, that he forgets hee is a Prieſt, and now makes that the <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> of Diuinity, which was before the <hi>handmaid.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> therefore in his Oration <hi>ad Catechum.</hi> expoſtulates with the hereticke, and by way of <hi>Proſopopeta</hi> doth catechize him thus, — <hi>Credis in Deum patrem omnipotentem? Doſt thou beleeue in God the father Almighty, &amp; in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord?</hi> I beleeue, thou ſayeſt: here, then thou art mine againſt the <hi>Pagan,</hi> and the <hi>Mahometan. Doſt thou beleeue that the God and man Chriſt Ieſus was conceiued of the holy Ghoſt, and borne of the Virgin Mary?</hi> I beleeue; thou art yet with me againſt <hi>Photinus,</hi> and the <hi>Iew. Doſt thou beleeue the father to be one perſon, and the ſonne another, yet father and ſonne but one God?</hi> and this alſo; here thou art mine too againſt the <hi>Sabellian. — Age ſi mecum es in omnibus, quare litigamus?</hi> ſaith the Father, if wee are one in all theſe, why contend we? <hi>Let there be no ſtrife betweene thee and me, for we are brethren.</hi> But it will fall out here anon as betweene <hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>Abraham, by reaſon of our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance we cannot dwell together,</hi> wee muſt part anon. Tell me then how is the ſonne equall to the father, in <hi>operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>beginning,</hi> in <hi>power</hi> or <hi>eternity,</hi> or <hi>both?</hi> In <hi>operation</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> the heretique allowes, but not <hi>eternitie; for how can that which was begotten be equall to that which was not begotten?</hi> Yes, <hi>eternitie,</hi> and <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> and <hi>power</hi> in God ſound one, for he is not <hi>great</hi> in one thing, and <hi>God</hi> in another, but in this <hi>great,</hi> that hee is <hi>God,</hi> be cauſe his <hi>greatneſſe</hi> is the ſame with his <hi>power,</hi> and his <hi>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> with his <hi>greatneſſe.</hi> Seeing then the ſonne is <hi>coequall</hi> in reſpect of <hi>power,</hi> he muſt be <hi>coeternall</hi> too in reſpect of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1978:11"/> 
               <hi>euerlaſtingneſſe.</hi> Here the <hi>Arrian</hi> is on fire, and nothing can allay or quench theſe flames but that which giues them an vntimely foment, Reaſon. To proue a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in nature is both troubleſome and difficult, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion without the aſſent of faith, impoſſible: In matters of reaſon, it is firſt <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> then <hi>reſolue,</hi> but in theſe of religion, firſt <hi>beleeue,</hi> and the effect will follow, whether for confeſſion of the truth, or conuiction of errour, or both. The greateſt miracles our Sauiour did in way of cure or reſtauration was with a — <hi>ſi credas</hi> —, and that to the <hi>liuing,</hi> and the <hi>dead,</hi> and betweene thoſe, the <hi>ſicke.</hi> To the Centurion for his ſeruant with a — <hi>ſicut credis —, As thou beleeueſt, ſo be it vnto thee, Matth.</hi> 8.5. To the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the <hi>Synagogue</hi> for his daughter, with a — <hi>Crede</hi> — too, — <hi>Feare not, but beleeue, Mar.</hi> 5.36. To all that are dumbe, or blinde, or lame in myſteries of Diuinity, as to thoſe dumbe, or blinde, or lame in bodie, with a — <hi>Vtrum cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditis? Doe you beleeue theſe things?</hi> then <hi>your faith hath made you whole, Matth.</hi> 9.28. but if wee meet with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weildy diſpoſitions, ſuch as are not onely vntractable, but oppoſite to the waies of faith, we ſhall rather drag than inuite them to beliefe; howeuer the Father labours here by a powerfull perſwaſion, and where hee failes in the ſtrength of proofe, he makes it out by way of alluſion, which he illuſtrates by a ſimilitude of <hi>fire</hi> &amp; <hi>light,</hi> which are diſtinct things, one proceeds from another, neither can the one be poſſibly without the other, the <hi>father</hi> he reſembles to the <hi>fire,</hi> the <hi>ſonne</hi> to the <hi>light,</hi> and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to deriue it (though obliquely ſomewhat) from ſacred ſtorie in <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.24. <hi>God</hi> is called a <hi>fire, — Thy God is a conſuming fire;</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>light, Thy word is a light vnto my ſteps:</hi> With this double ſtone he batters the forehead both of the <hi>Sabellian,</hi> and the <hi>Arrian;</hi> firſt of the <hi>Sabellian,</hi> for here are two in one, <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>light,</hi> yet two ſtill not one, why not ſo with <hi>Sonne,</hi> and <hi>Father?</hi> The <hi>Arrian</hi> next, for here alſo is one borne of another,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1978:11"/> yet the one not poſſibly to be borne without the other, neither of them <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>laſt; fire</hi> and <hi>light</hi> coequall, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>Sonne,</hi> ſo too. The ſimilitude iarres onely in this, thoſe are <hi>temporarie,</hi> and theſe <hi>eternall, — pater ergo &amp; filius vnum ſunt</hi> (ſaith the Father) — <hi>Sunt — dico, quia pater &amp; filius, — vnum — quia Deus; dualitas in prole, vnitas in deitate, cum dico filius, alter eſt, cum dico Deus, vnus eſt. cont.</hi> 5. <hi>hoſt. genera cap.</hi> 7. What more obuious and trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to the thinneſt knowledge, than that there is here — <hi>alius</hi> and — <hi>alias,</hi> but not — <hi>aliud</hi> —, as in bels of equal magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and dimenſion (pardon the lowneſſe of the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude) which though framed out of the ſame <hi>maſſe,</hi> and <hi>Art,</hi> where the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> and <hi>workmanſhip</hi> are one, yet the <hi>ſound</hi> is diuers; for though of Sonne and Father the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> be one as <hi>God,</hi> yet the appellation and <hi>ſound</hi> is diuers, as <hi>Sonne</hi> and <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Heretique either impatient of this truth, or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, once more makes reaſon his vmpire, but how ſiniſterly, how iniuriouſly? that which ſhould be the miſtreſſe of our ſence, and the Sterne and arbitreſſe of all our actions, muſt now be a promotreſſe and baud to error. It is bold expoſtulation that runnes vs on theſe ſhelues of danger, and hath been the often wracke of many a blooming and hopefull truth. There are errours beſides theſe deſperate, of will, of vnderſtanding, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times are rather voluntary, than deliberatiue, and balla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced more by the ſuggeſtions of a weake fancy, than any ſtrength of iudgement; If our thoughts ſtill lie at Hull in thoſe ſhallowes of nature, where we coaſt daily about ſence and reaſon, how can we but daſh againſt vntimely errours? but if we keepe aloofe in principles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where thoſe winds of doubt and diſtruſt ſwell and bluſter not, faith will be at laſt our wafter vnto truth. Let's not then any longer root our meditations in vallies vnder vs, but looke vp to <hi>thoſe hills from whence our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation commeth.</hi> Let's conuerſe a little with Prophets
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1978:12"/> and Euangeliſts, and thoſe other Regiſters and Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Almightie. — <hi>In te eſt Deus, &amp; non eſt Deus praeter te, Eſay</hi> 45.5. Infidell, either deny a diuinity of <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Sonne,</hi> or confeſſe an <hi>vnitie</hi> of both; for one thou muſt doe; of the <hi>Sonne</hi> thou canſt not, for there is a God in him, the <hi>Father, Pater qui in me manet ipſe loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> the <hi>Father that is in me he ſpeaketh, and the works which I doe be doth Ioh.</hi> 10. of the <hi>Father</hi> thou dar'ſt not, there is a God in him the <hi>Sonne, — I am in the Father, and the Father in me, Ioh.</hi> 14. Here then is both a <hi>proprietie of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and <hi>vnitie of conſent. God</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> yet not <hi>two,</hi> but <hi>one,</hi> fulneſſe of diuinitie in the <hi>Father,</hi> fulneſſe in the <hi>Son,</hi> yet the <hi>Godhead</hi> not <hi>diuers,</hi> but the <hi>ſame,</hi> ſo that now there is no leſſe a ſingleneſſe of <hi>name</hi> than <hi>operation.</hi> And therefore thoſe words of the Apoſtle, though in the firſt encounter and ſuruay, they offer a ſhew of contradiction, yet ſearched to the quicke and kernell, are not without a myſterious weight, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. It is ſaid of the Father, — <hi>Filio proprio non pepercit, ſed pro nobis tradidit —. He ſpared not his owne Sonne but</hi> gaue <hi>him for vs all to death;</hi> yet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 5. It is ſaid of the Sonne, — <hi>Tradidit ſemetcipſum pro nobis —, — He gaue himſelfe for vs</hi> —, Heere is a double — <hi>Tradidit</hi> — an a — <hi>pronobis</hi> —, and a — <hi>ſepronobis</hi> —, if he was <hi>giuen</hi> of the Father, and yet <hi>gaue</hi> himſelfe, how can it follow, but that there muſt be both a ſimpathy of <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>operation?</hi> And indeed it were a meere ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and robbery of their honour, to depriue them of this ſo ſacred a correſpondence. We allow to all belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers but one ſoule and one heart, <hi>Acts</hi> 4 to all thoſe that cleaue to God <hi>one ſpirit.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. to husband and wife <hi>one fleſh,</hi> to all men in reſpect of nature, but <hi>one ſubſtance;</hi> If in ſublunary matters (where there is no alliance or reference with thoſe more ſacred) Scriptures approue many to be one, ſhall we riffle the Father and the Sonne of the like Iuriſdiction, and deny them to be <hi>eternally one,</hi> where there is no iarre of <hi>will,</hi> or <hi>ſubſtance?</hi> Heare how the Apoſtle doth chalke out a way to our beleefe, by the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1978:12"/> rules of diuine truth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. <hi>There is one God which is the Father, of whom are all things, and we of him, and one Lord Ieſus Chriſt by whom are all things, and wee by him.</hi> Here is — <hi>Deus</hi> — and — <hi>Dominus</hi> —, a <hi>God</hi> and a <hi>Lord,</hi> and yet no pluralitie of <hi>Godhead,</hi> and an — <hi>ex quo</hi> — and a — <hi>per quem, — of whom</hi> and <hi>by whom,</hi> yet a vnitie of <hi>power,</hi> for as in that he ſayes <hi>one Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> he denied not the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> to be <hi>Lord,</hi> ſo by ſaying one God the <hi>Father,</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied not the <hi>Sonne</hi> to be <hi>God. — In te igitur eſt Deus per vnitatem naturae, &amp; non eſt Deus</hi> praeter te <hi>propter proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ſubſtantiae. Ambroſ. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de fide ad Gratian</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> With what ſacred inſcriptions do we find him blazoned, the <hi>ingrauen forme of his Father,</hi> the <hi>image of his goodneſſe,</hi> the <hi>brightneſſe of his glory?</hi> and with theſe three of an Apoſtle, <note place="margin">Eſay 9.6.</note> a Prophet rankes other three not ſubordinate in maieſtie, or truth; as if the ſame inſpiration had dictated both matter and forme. <hi>Counſellor,</hi> the <hi>Almighty God,</hi> the <hi>euerlaſting Father,</hi> the <hi>euerlaſting Father</hi> in a double ſence, either as he is <hi>author</hi> of it, as <hi>Iuball</hi> was ſaid to be the <hi>Father</hi> of Muſicke when he was but the <hi>Author</hi> or inuentor, or in reſpect of his <hi>affection,</hi> becauſe hee loues with an <hi>euerlaſting loue;</hi> yet ſome leaning on the word of the Greeke Interpreter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, which the vulgar renders, — <hi>Pater futuri ſeculi</hi> — would reſtraine it onely to the life to come, but <hi>Caluine</hi> extends it to a perpetuity of time and continued <hi>Series</hi> of all ages; <note place="margin">In cap. 9. Eſay.</note> And the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dee</hi> tranſlation (which with the <hi>Hebrew</hi> is moſt authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique) ſeemes not onely to aſſent to it, but applaud it too. — <hi>Nomen eius ab</hi> ante <hi>mirabilis conſilio, Deus fortis, perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens in ſaecula ſaculorum</hi> —. Howeuer the <hi>Septuagint</hi> (ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with the maieſtie of ſo great a name) giue it vs by — <hi>Magni confilij Angelus</hi> —; which words though they haue no footing in the originall, yet both <hi>Auguſtire</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> approue the ſence, taking — <hi>Angelus</hi> — for — <hi>Nancius</hi> —, ſo that <hi>Chriſt</hi> tooke not vpon him the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of an Angell (as ſome would iniuriouſly foize upon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1978:13"/> 
               <hi>Origens</hi> opinion) but the <hi>office,</hi> by which as a <hi>Legate</hi> or <hi>mediator,</hi> rather he appeared to thoſe <hi>Patriarches</hi> of old, <hi>Abraham</hi> and the reſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.3.</p>
            <p>I haue once more brought Chriſt as farre as <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> but the Text tells me a little farther, and ſo doth my aduerſary too, till I haue verified in <hi>Chriſt</hi> the ſtrength of that voice, <hi>I am the</hi> God <hi>of Abraham,</hi> and the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iacob.</hi> We may not leaue him here with the bare title of an <hi>Angell,</hi> we muſt goe higher, to that of the <hi>Sonne of God,</hi> where we ſhall meet our implacable <hi>Arrian</hi> in his violent oppoſition. <hi>If there be a Sonne, hee muſt be borne, if borne, there was a time when there was no Sonne, for to be borne, preſuppoſes a beginning, and that time.</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> diuided (as it ſeemes) betweene pity and indignation, anſweres. <hi>Qui hoc dicit non intelligit etiam natum eſſe, deo ſempiternum eſſe —. To be borne with God, is to be eternall with God,</hi> and he opens himſelfe by his old ſimilitude, <hi>Sicut ſplendor qui gignitur ab igni,</hi> as light which is begotten of fire, and diffuſed, is coequall with the fire, and would be coeternall too if fire were eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, ſo the Sonne with the Father, <hi>this</hi> being before all time, the <hi>other</hi> muſt kiſſe in the ſame <hi>euerlaſtingneſſe.</hi> The Father thinking his reaſon built too ſlenderly doth buttreſſe (as it were) and backe it with the authoritie of an Apoſtle, <note place="margin">1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſuch an Apoſtle as was ſometimes a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and therefore his authoritie moſt potent againſt a perſecutor, where he ſtiles Chriſt, <hi>the power and wiſedome of God.</hi> If the Sonne of God be the power and wiſdome of God, and that God was neuer without <hi>power</hi> and <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> how can we ſcant the Sonne of a coeternitie with the Father? For either we muſt grant that there was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a Sonne, or that God had ſometimes no wiſedome, and impudence or madneſſe were neuer at ſuch a growth of blaſphemie as to belch the latter. If the reuerend alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of a learned Prelate, or thoſe more ſacred of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, cannot bung vp the mouth of a malicious Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1978:13"/> heare the voice of a Prophet, &amp; a Father warbling vpon that too. <hi>Before me there was no other God, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me there ſhall be none, Eſay.</hi> 43.10. <hi>Quis hoc dicit, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, an filius?</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) who is here the ſpeaker, the Father or the Sonne (he comes ouer him with a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till <hi>Dilemma:</hi>) if the Sonne, thus he ſaith, — <hi>before mee there was no other God,</hi> if the Father, — <hi>After me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>there ſhall be none,</hi> for both the Father in the Sonne, and the Sonne in the Father muſt be knowne, when thou nameſt a Father, thou haſt alſo deſigned a Sonne, becauſe no man is a Father to himſelfe; when thou nameſt a Sonne, thou confeſſeſt alſo a Father, for no man is ſonne to himſelfe, the Sonne therefore can neither ſubſiſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Father, nor the Father without the Sonne, the one being from euerlaſting, we may not depoſe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the like omnipotency. If truth thus twiſted in a triple authoritie of <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles, Fathers,</hi> cannot allay the turbulency of a contagious heretique, heare the voyce of him who ſpake as neuer man ſpake; neuer Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, Apoſtle, Prophet, (if at length ſuch an authoritie be paſſable with an <hi>Arrian</hi>) the Lambe of God; <hi>O Father glorifie me with thine owne ſelfe, with the glory which I had with thee before the world was, Ioh.</hi> 17.5. Heareſt thou In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell? a Sonne, and glorified, with the Father before the world? what chinke now, what by-path for euaſion where thou art compaſſed with ſuch a cloud of witneſſes?</p>
            <p>Tell me deuill (for hereticke is to cheape and low an attribute, when thou art growne to ſuch a maturity and height of prophanation) was there a time when omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent God the Father was not, and yet was there a God? <hi>Gird now vp thy loynes, and anſwer if thou canſt,</hi> for if he began to be a Father, then he was firſt a God, and after made a Father, how is God then immutable, how the ſame one, when by acceſſe of generation he ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer change? Grant mee then a God eternall, and thou muſt a Father, and if a Father, a ſonne too, they are rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1978:14"/> and cannot digeſt a ſeparation either in reſpect of time, or power. And this thou didſt once ſubſcribe to (and I know not what deuilliſh ſuggeſtion wrought thy reuolt) in an Epiſtle to <hi>Euſebius,</hi> if the authority of <hi>Bren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> will paſſe for claſſicall, where thou couldſt afford him the ſtile of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>plenus Deus, vnigenitus</hi> — and a little before that he had his beginning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> — <hi>ante tempora, ante ſaecula,</hi> why ſhouldſt thou now then rip vp the wombe of Deity, and enquire how he was begotten? how borne? and when? as if thou labouredſt to baſtard his deſcent, and make it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary. Doe not, doe not out of the cuſtome of humane generation tie eternity to time, or manner, and ſo at once vomit errour and blaſphemy. Heare the voice of the Lord thundring vnto thee, <hi>Cui me ſimilem exiſtimas?</hi> who is like vnto mee, or to whom is the arme of the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed? <hi>Me ante montes generauit Dominus,</hi> before the mountaines were ſetled, or the hills raiſed, I was brought forth. <note place="margin">Ambroſ. 1. de fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, cap. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Habeat ergo generationis inuſitatae gloriam, qui ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet poteſtatis inuſitatae gratiam.</hi> He that hath an vnwon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Iuriſdiction in reſpect of power, it were a derogation too capitall to leſſen his prerogatiue in way of birth; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue what pompe he carrieth of antiquity, what deſcent, how deriued? by <hi>Heraulds</hi> of no meane ranke, a <hi>King,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and a Prophet that's a <hi>King, I was ſet vp of old, from euerlaſting,</hi> Prou. 8.24. <hi>His goings forth haue beene from euerlaſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g,</hi> Mich. 5.2. <hi>Thy throne is eſtabliſhed of old, thou art from euerlaſting,</hi> Pſal. 93.2. Harke, from <hi>euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting,</hi> from <hi>euerlaſting,</hi> from <hi>euerlaſting,</hi> one ecchoing to another, as if the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me pen had beene as well the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrix of the languages, as the truth. If thou ſhalt then hereafter ball an eternity with a — <hi>quande,</hi> or a — <hi>quomodo natus?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amb. vt ſupra.</note> I goe one with the Father ſtill, <hi>Quid te iſta quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionum tormenta delectant? Audis Dei filium, aut dele nomen, aut agnoſce natura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? — Quaeres</hi> that are to nice ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther torment the vnderſtanding, than informe it, and are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1978:14"/> more apt to puzzle our Iudgement, than to rectifie it. Subtilty of queſtions (I know not whether) it hath more conuinced, or begotten errour, or improued vs in our knowledge, or ſtaggered vs. And hence I ſuppoſe was the ſubſtance of the Apoſtles aduice to the <hi>Romanes, He that is weake in faith receiue you;</hi> but not to doubtfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>putations, <hi>Cap.</hi> 14.1. Curioſities of queſtion haue euer beene the engines and ſtales to hereſie, and therfore ſome of the Fathers haue nicke-named <hi>Philoſophers</hi> with an — <hi>Haereticorum Patriarchae</hi> — <note place="margin">Tertull.</note> It is no leſſe a pollicy than right in ſadder learning to giue Diuinity the chaire, for if Arts with their ſubtle retinue once inuade it, ſence and reaſon will hiſſe faith out of doores. And therefore we finde the ſame Apoſtle vehement in his — <hi>Cauete ne vos ſeducat,</hi> Beware leſt any man <hi>ſpoile you through Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy and vaine deceit, after the tradition of men, after the rudiments of the world, and not after Chriſt,</hi> Coloſſ. 2.4. In matters of faith he that plaies either the Philoſopher, or the criticke diſplaies neither his Iudgement, nor his Religion, for <hi>the kingdome of God is not in word, but in power,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.20. <hi>Conſidera</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>quod voceris fidelis non rationalis,</hi> Faith, not reaſon, is our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor in this depth, and beleefe, not ſcruple is our ſteerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to our port. Wiſdome, I meane that which is worldly and feathered (as it were) with tranſtorineſſe, muſt now ſtoope to ſimplicity, ſtrength to weakneſſe. How doth the Apoſtle iumpe with vs? <hi>Hee hath choſen the fooliſh things of this world to confound the wiſe, and the weake things the mighty,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.27. Hence it is that the kingdome of heauen belongs vnto children, Matth. 19.13. And God hath hid it from the prudent, and reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it to babes, Matth. 11.25. And therefore S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> makes a proud knowledge ſtrike ſaile to a modeſt ignorance in his 188. <hi>Serm. de Temp. — Meum eſt pie ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantiam confiteri, quam temere mihi ſcientiam vendica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi> In ſacred matters your nimble Cryticiſmes are as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1978:15"/> to deſperatneſſe, as danger; to be curious (here) is to be quaintly madde, and thus to thruſt into the bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber of the Almighty is a franticke ſawcineſſe. Who can vnlocke thoſe Coffers of omnipotency, <note place="margin">Eſay 45.2.</note> 
               <hi>but he that breakes in peeces the gates of Braſſe, and cuts in ſunder the barres of Iron?</hi> Who thoſe Cabinets of abſtruſer know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? <note place="margin">Jdem, ibid.</note> but he <hi>that giues thee the treaſure of darkneſſe, and hidden riches of ſecret places?</hi> How can our low built ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions but flag in the expreſſion of ſuch a birth, when we finde a Prophet ſo tranſported with contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of it, that he dares the world with an Interrogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, — <hi>Generationem eius quis enarrabit? Who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his generation,</hi> Eſay 53. Yet we haue met with ſome ſupercilious and daring wits, which venture here to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twiſt this myſterie of generation, as if they would calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late an eternall birthright, leaning vpon the authority of <hi>S. Hierom</hi> in his Commentaries vpon <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1. where he aſſeuers, that in ſacred Scriptures — <hi>Quis</hi> oftentimes is not put for an <hi>impoſſibility,</hi> but a <hi>difficulty.</hi> And hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in this — <hi>Quis</hi> — of <hi>Eſay, Generationem eius quis enarrabit?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib 1. diſt. 19.</note> But <hi>Lumbard</hi> doth both vindicate and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the Father, thus, — <hi>Non dicit quod generatio filij ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna.</hi> — He ſaies not that this eternall generation of the ſonne of God can deſcend to any mortall capacity in an abſolute and full knowledge; but in ſome meaſure and degree, for ſo the Apoſtle doth peece-out our perfection here, <hi>We are happy in part, and know onely in part,</hi> not a haire, not a feather as we ſhould. <hi>Dic mihi</hi> (ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>) <note place="margin">Orat. contra Arrianos.</note> 
               <hi>altitudinem Coeli, profundum Abyſſi, &amp;c.</hi> Shew me the height of Heauen, and the depth of Hell, number (if thou canſt) the ſands of the Sea, the drops of raine, or the haires of thine owne head. Plane mee out by ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect demonſtration the truth of thoſe things which gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell here below, and I will beleeue thy knowledge may aſpire to thoſe which are aboue; but thou haſt no power of compaſſing the one, nor poſſibility in the atchieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1978:15"/> of the other. For when all thy faculties of <hi>vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, will,</hi> haue fluttered ſo high as the wings of nature can eleuate and mount them to, yet thou wilt at laſt make vp the ſtorie of <hi>Icarus,</hi> and finde that theſe are but waxen plumes, and will melt at the preſence of thoſe glorious beames, and ſo thy fall will be as diſhonourable as thy at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt was peremptory; for if the great Doctour of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> (rapt vp into the third Heauen) ſaid that hee heard words vnexpreſſable, which no tongue dated to vtter, how canſt thou diſſolue and vntie — <hi>Paternae ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerationis Arcana</hi> — (as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſtiles them) thoſe knots and Riddles of eternall generation, which can neuer bore a humane intellect, nor lie within the verge of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall apprehenſion? <hi>Mihi enim impoſſibile eſt generatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſcire ſecretum</hi> (ſaith the Father) <hi>mens deficit, vox ſilet, non meae tantum, ſed &amp; Angelorum, ſupra poteſtates, &amp; ſepra Cherubin, &amp; ſupra Seraphin, &amp; ſupra omnem ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi> in his 1. <hi>de fide ad Gratian. c.</hi> 4. It is not then ſo much ambition in our deſire, as madneſſe, to attempt the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that where there is an impoſſibility of reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thoſe enterprizes are temerarious and ouer-head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong, which put on where there is not onely danger, but a deſpaire of conqueſt. How can reaſonable man but lie buried vnder the weight of ſuch a myſterie, at which thoſe grand pillars of the Church haue not onely ſhooke but ſhrunke? How muſt wee be ſtrucke dumbe when the tongues of Saints and Angels ſtutter? How our mindes entranced, when the glorious hoaſt of Heauen, and all thoſe feathered <hi>Hierarchies</hi> ſhal clap their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings? All reaſons tongue-tied, all apprehenſion non pluſt, all vnderſtanding darkened; ſo that I may now ſpeake of this metaphoricall depth, as <hi>Iob</hi> did of that other naturall, — <hi>Thou haſt made a cloud the garment thereof, and thicke darkneſſe a ſwadling band.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Myſteries carry with them ſuch an awe and Maieſtie, as if they would be obeyed, not diſputed, and aſſented to,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1978:16"/> not controuerſt. In ſecrets without bottome (ſuch as carry the ſtampe of ſacred) except faith holds vs vp like children we ſwimme without bladders, and muſt either dabble to the ſhore, or ſinke, reaſon hath not an hand to lend vs. Faith and reaſon in reſpect of myſterie, are as a wheele and a bucket at a deepe well; faith hath both the power and ſafetie of deſcent, and nimbly fathoms it, whilſt reaſon wheele's, and rounds it, and is ſtrangely giddied in a diſtracted <hi>Gyre.</hi> And indeed who durſt laue ſuch an Ocean, <note place="margin">Eſay 44 7.</note> but he <hi>that ſayes to the deepes be drie?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 38.8.</note> 
               <hi>or can ſhut vp the ſeas with doores, that they breake not out, and ſay, hither ſhalt thou come, no farther, there ſhall thy proud waues ſtay?</hi> What eye that lookes on the Sunne, and dazels not, <note place="margin">Ecclus 10.19.</note> but he <hi>that ſees from euerlaſting to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting? &amp; ſends out lightning that they may come and goe, and ſay, here we are?</hi> The ſtar-gazer and bold figure flinger are at a ſtand here, why lookeſt thou vp thou proud A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologer? you men of <hi>Galilee,</hi> why gaze you into heauen? Thus ſaith the Lord of hoaſts, he that form'd thee from the wombe: <note place="margin">Eſay 44.24,25.</note> 
               <hi>I am the Lord that maketh all things,</hi> that <hi>ſtretcheth out the heauens alone, that fruſtrateth the tokens of lyars, and maketh diuiners mad, that turneth wiſemen backwards, and maketh their knowledge fooliſhneſſe. Thou, O Lord, ſhalt haue them in deriſion, thou ſhalt laugh the heathen to ſcorne, for the ſinne of their mouth, and the words of their lips they ſhall be taken in their pride, as the duſt (O Lord) ſhalt thou driue and ſcatter them, and in thy wrath thou ſhalt conſume them, that they may know, that it is God that ruleth in Iaacob, and to the end of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arrius</hi> is now in his pompe and height of glory, and flouriſheth like a greene bay-tree, anone looke after him, and hee is no where to bee found. Hee is vp yet, but it is with the proud man in the <hi>Pſalmes, in ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery places,</hi> and (anone) with him, how ſuddenly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, periſhed, and brought to a fearefull end? The whole Eaſterne Church is now in a ſtrange combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1978:16"/> and he muſt kindle it, by and by thoſe flames ſhall light him to his owne ruine. Hereſie may root and bud, and branch, and grow to a goodly height, but the hand of vengeance houers ouer it, and when it ſtrikes, it fels it at a blow, and it comes downe like a pine from a ſteepe mountaine, which in the fall ſhatters both the branch, and bodie. It is heere, as with miſts and fogges which we ſee firſt riſe as in a thin ſmoake from a low Fen or Valley, but gathering ſtrength climbe the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and at laſt ſo thicken in one body of vapours that they ſeeme to dare the Earth with a ſecond night, till the Sunne (recouering height and power) by the vertue and ſubtiltie of his beames doth diſſipate and open them, and they are ſeene no more.</p>
            <p>Will you haue a preſident? we find <hi>Arrius</hi> at firſt a meane Prieſt of <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> a man keene and ſubtill, as well in wit as learning, <hi>Specie, &amp; forma magis, quàm virtute religioſus, ſed gloria, &amp; nouitatis improbè cupidus,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ruffinus</hi>) <note place="margin">Lib. 1.</note> In vertue not ſo much refined as in the deportment of the outward man, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed a ſet grauity, though no truth of Religion, in a thirſt and purſuit of honour and noueltie, ſtrangely vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, — <hi>Dulcis erat incollequio, perſuadens animas, &amp; blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diens.</hi> In his diſcourſe no leſſe ſweet, than powerfull, and where he gaines no conqueſt by perſwaſion, he mines by flattery; Thus by the ſorceries and enchantments of a voluble tong, ſimplicity is betrayed, and vnder a pretext of truth, ſilly women (who are euer moſt affected with leuity and change) are firſt led captiue; and theſe for the enhancement &amp; propagation of their new doctrine, commerce with their allies, and theſe tickled with new fancies, applaud the deſigne, entertaine the noueltie, conuenticles are both conſulted on, and ſummoned, and in a ſhort time, — <hi>Septingentas virginitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profeſſas in vnam contraxit</hi> — So <hi>Epiphanius</hi> —. <note place="margin">Aduerſ. Haereſ.</note> Their Religion is yet in the blade, and greene onely in a few ſhe diſciples, anone
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1978:17"/> it growes by their league with others, <note place="margin">Amb. 1. de fide cap 4.</note> 
               <hi>Eudoxius, Eunomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Aetius</hi> and <hi>Demophilus, plura nomina, ſed vna perfidia</hi> —; Coheires though not to the ſame title, the ſame villany; ſo that thoſe dangerous tumults in the body of the Church could not but now ſtartle the head and gouernour. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> is informed of thoſe pernicious and deſperate proceedings, who calls a Councell of 318 Biſhops for the condemnation of the heretique. Some conuerſant in ſubtiltie of queſtion (as there was neuer opinion ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, but found a Champion to propugne it) fauoured <hi>Arrius;</hi> but at length moſt of them decreed with one mouth Chriſt to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, 17 a while ſticke faſt to the opinion of the Heretique, 11 whereof by the menacing of the Emperour ſubſcribed, <hi>Manu ſolum, non mente,</hi> and the other 6 are now with <hi>Arrius</hi> vpon termes of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile; they betake themſelues to <hi>Paleſtina,</hi> where partly by ſtrength of Argument, partly by the inſinuations of a ſmooth tongue, they gaine other Biſhops to their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Anon, <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and <hi>Valens</hi> Emperours; ſome they ſeduce by ſubtilty, ſome by gifts, ſome by power, ſome by cruelty; thoſe that affied conſtantly to the profeſſion of Chriſts diuinity, they inuade by perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; all the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty tortures that malice or tyranny could deuiſe, are now put in practiſe, for the torment of thoſe profeſſors; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the hearts of their very enemies, could nor but thaw into pitty to heare the cries, but conſtancy of little children vnder the barbarous hands of their mercileſſe tormentors. <hi>Chriſtianus ſum. Chriſtum verum Deum, credo, &amp; adoro,</hi> as the author in his <hi>hiſtoria tripartita de perſequutione. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andalorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This hereſie now is full blowne, and at the growth; one Act more makes it ripe, and ready for the ſickle. <hi>Alexandria</hi> is yet infected, and foule dregs of <hi>Arria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme</hi> reigne not onely here, but in the neighbour Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces; Inſomuch that <hi>Alexander</hi> (then Biſhop) daily peſtered with thoſe damned innouations, on a Sunday,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1978:17"/> (for ſo my <hi>Antiquary</hi> tels me) <note place="margin">Epiphanius.</note> earneſtly prayed that God would either take him away leſt he ſhould be defiled with the like contagion, or that he would ſhew ſome miracle, either for the conuerſion or confuſion of the Heretique. Not long after the deſires of the holy man were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, and in ſuch a way of iudgement, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation would ſute better with a ring of Scauengers than a noble throng, his bowels burſt, as ſometimes <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> did, <hi>Et ſic finem adeptus eſt, in loco immundo &amp; graue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olenti,</hi> — his death was equally odious with his life, and that with the place he died in, no ſad retinue or pompe of exequy to embalme him, no hearſe or winding ſheet, but his owne intrailes, and grau'd vp with excrements, inſteed of earth, an end as odious, as vntimely, as if it proceeded from the hand of vengeance, and not Fate.</p>
            <p>And ſo Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> dilates on it <note place="margin">1 de fide cap. 5.</note> — <hi>Non eſt fortuita mors vbi in ſacrilegio pari, poenae parile pregeſſit exemplum, vt idem ſubirent ſuppliciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, qui eundem Dominum negaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt &amp; eundem Dominum prodiderunt</hi> —. It is no caſuall, but a deſtinated end, that in a like ſactiledge, there ſhould be a like example of puniſhment, and ſo both meet in one way of ruine which had denied and betrayed their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            <p>I haue now brought this hereſie to her graue, but the funerall of this is the reſurrection of another, and the re-intertainment of that of a third. No part of Chriſt (either in reſpect of his diuinitie, or manhood) but is the mint of a new hereſie, which (if I ſhould indeuour (heere) either to confute or open) would proue an vndertaking fitter for a volume, than a diſcourſe, and for a Library, than a volume. It coſt the houres of an intire age, and the ſweat and elaborateneſſe of all the Fathers. Thoſe few ſands which are now in their conſtant courſe will be runne out in the very nomination of <hi>Marcionites, Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinians, Hebionites, Apollinarians,</hi> and the reſidue of that curſed rabble, and ſo I ſhall be caſt vpon your cenſures,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1978:18"/> if not as I haue been weake, yet as I haue beene tedious. I will then open the mouthes of very heathens, and they ſhall both ſpeake, and confirme this truth, and no leſſe appoſe our aduerſaries, than conuince them, an authority I know not how vnſauory or vnſeaſonable to a diuided Auditory, where a prophane quotation ſounds ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as heatheniſh as a tradition, which in the very name is cri'de downe as apocryphall, and Romaniſh; but I muſt put that vpon the hazard, not eſteeming the froth either of popular cenſure or approbation.</p>
            <p>Heathens indeed are little aboue the condition of beaſts, if that onely actuate a man which animates a Chriſtian, the ſoule of faith; yet if God pleaſe to caſt his pearles before theſe ſwine, wherefore hath hee made vs Lords ouer them, but to vindicate thoſe hallowed and pretious things from the hands of vniuſt poſſeſſors? <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clara Ethnicorum dicta Theologica ab ijs, tanquàm iniuſtis poſſeſſoribus, in vſum noſtrum transferenda.</hi> It is <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> in his ſecond booke <hi>De doctrina Chriſtiana</hi> 4. <hi>chap.</hi> Diuine truth in Heathen mouthes is like the Iewels in Egyptian hands, their wants no Alchimiſt to refine the mettle, onely ſome diſcreeter Iſraelite to transferre the vſe; he that was brought vp at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> to the ignorant Idolaters of <hi>Athens,</hi> concludes againſt them from the mouth of their owne Poets, — <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as ſome of your owne Poets haue ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. Text enough to gaine, I ſay, not autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, but applauſe to his diſcourſe, and to conuince the Heathens ſhame, if not their faith. Diue with me a little farther into their ſecrets, and we ſhall find amongſt much <hi>Hay</hi> and <hi>Stubble,</hi> ſome <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Pretious ſtones,</hi> doctrines which want no truth to make them ſound, onely diuine authoritie to make them authentique. It was not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the true light which ſhines on euery man that commeth into the world, ſhould glimpſe into thoſe that <hi>ſate in darkneſſe, and in the ſhadow of death;</hi> For old
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1978:18"/> 
               <hi>Simplicianus</hi> in <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> Confeſſions 8. Booke 2. Chapter, giues incouragement to a particular enquiry, and concludes in certaine books of the Platoniſts — <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um inſinuari, &amp; cius verbum</hi> —. And of this <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>the Word,</hi> the very Philoſophers were not ignorant, for wee meet with a <hi>Hermes,</hi> and a — <hi>Zenon,</hi> ſtiling the maker &amp; orderer of the Vniuerſe — <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> — <hi>The Word</hi> — which they inlarge with other attributes of — <hi>Fate, neceſſity, God</hi> — &amp; what ſauours a little of a heatheniſh relique — <hi>Animu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iouis</hi> — taking — <hi>Iupiter</hi> — in the ſence that they doe <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his 4. booke <hi>de vera Sapient. cap.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>But why doe we rob them of their maiden honour, and take their ſayings vpon Tradition meerly? let them ſpeake themſelues in their peculiar and mother-tongue. <hi>Numenius,</hi> a famous Pythagorian (one, who twixt <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> put no difference but of Language, calling <hi>Plato — Moſen, Attica Lingua Loquentem, — Moſes</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Atticke Dialect) <hi>Deus primus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in ſcip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo quidem exiſtens, eſt ſimplex, propterea quòd ſecum ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per eſt, nunquam diuiſus; Secundus, &amp; tertius eſt vnus:</hi> The firſt God is alwaies exiſtent in himſelfe, ſimple, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuiſible, the ſecond and third one; and a little after, he calls this firſt God — <hi>Creautis Dei patrem, — The father of the creating God.</hi> Had they all adored what he here ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, a Trinity in vnity (ſo to be worſhipped) I ſhould then propoſe their precept not onely to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, but their practice to be imitated. Search on, and loe that rich mine of Truth is not yet at her droſſe, or bottome, for <hi>Heraclitus</hi> next, one who was wont to call <hi>S. Iohn, Barbarian,</hi> that Euangeliſt to whom belonged the Eagle, as well for ſublimity of Stile, as Contemplation; he — <hi>cenſet verbum Dei in ordine Principij, atque digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate conſtitutum, apud Deum eſſe, &amp; Deum eſſe, in quo quicquid factum ſit, fuerit viuens, &amp; vita, &amp; ens, tum in corpora Lapſum, carnemque indutum, hominem apparuiſſe, oſtendens etiam tunc naturae ſuae magnitudinem:</hi> Harke
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1978:19"/> how the <hi>Frog</hi> chaunts like the <hi>Nightingale,</hi> (It is <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milians, Ethnici audiendi, non tanquam Philomelae, ſed Ranae</hi>) and curiouſly counterfeits her in euery ſtraine? How cloſely this obſcure Heathen followes not onely the Goſpels truth, but the phraſe too? <hi>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and was God, all things were made by him, euery liuing Creature, life, and thing, then this Word was made fleſh, and appeared man,</hi> &amp; <hi>euen then ſhewed the glory of his nature.</hi> How ſweetly he warbles with his Barbarian, as if by an eaſie labour of Tranſlation hee had bereft him both of Truth and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence? I maruaile not now at that Teſtimony of <hi>Baſil the Great,</hi> vpon thoſe words, <hi>In principio erat verbum — Hoc ego noui, multos etiam extra veritatis rationem poſitos</hi> — I haue knowne many (ſaith he) and thoſe put without the pale and liſt of diuine Truth, men meerely ſecular, aduancing and magnifying this peece of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and at length bold to mixe it with their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and writings. And S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſeconds it with an inſtance, — <hi>Quidam Platonicus,</hi> — A certaine Platoniſt was wont to ſay that <hi>the beginning of S. Iohns Goſpell was worthy to be written in letters of gold, and preached in the moſt eminent Churches and Congregations,</hi> in his 10 book <hi>de Ciuitate Dei, c.</hi> 29. O the diuine raptures and infuſions, that God doth ſometimes betroth to his very enemies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who can but conceiue that as the very worſt of men haue knowledge enough to make them inexcuſable; ſo the beſt of Heathen had enough to make them Saints, were their faith that he ſhould be their Sauiour, as great as their knowledge, that he was the Sonne of God. With what rich Epithites they bedecke and crowne him. — <hi>Mentis Germen, Verbum Lucens, Dei Filius,</hi> (it is his ſaying, who (I know not by what ſearch) found out almoſt all Truth, <hi>Mercurius Triſmegiſtus</hi>) <hi>the mindes bloſſome, the word that gaue light, the ſonne of God.</hi> What elſe did S. <hi>Iohn</hi> adde, but that the word <hi>was</hi> light? And S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:1978:19"/> giues this farther teſtimony of that heathen, that he ſpake many things of Chriſt in a propheticke manner — <hi>eadem veritate, licet non eodem Animi affectu</hi> — with the ſame truth the Prophets did, but not with the ſame affection — <hi>pronunciabat illa Hermes. Dolendo, pronunciabat hac Propheta, Gaudendo</hi> — in his 8. booke <hi>de Ciuitate Dei,</hi> 23. chapter. And why ſhould we batre ſome of their Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers of a propheticke knowledge, when a Poet ſhall fill his cheekes with a — <hi>Chara Deum Soboles, Magnum Iouis incrementum</hi> —? And if wee looke backe to thoſe Oracles of old, the <hi>Sybills</hi> ſacred Raptures, we ſhall finde them more like a Chriſtians Comment, than a Heathens Prediction.
<q>
                  <l>Tunc ad mortales veniet, mortalibus ipſis</l>
                  <l>In terris ſimilis, natus Patris omnipotentis</l>
                  <l>Corpore veſtitus — </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Whereof if we enquire a little into the originall, Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In oration. contra Arrian.</note> will tell vs that the Greeke coppies giue vs <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> — <hi>Ieſus Chriſt, the Sonne of God, the Sauiour;</hi> and it is not onely probable, but euident, that the Gentiles had a knowledge of Chriſt as he was the <hi>Word,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note>as it appeareth by that of <hi>Serapis</hi> vnto <hi>Thulis, King of Egypt.</hi> And it is ſtrangely remarkeable: what wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Titles, and inſcriptions, the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> dedicate to his name and memory, with which as (with a wreath and Lawrell) they girt &amp; beautifie his Temples, — <hi>Dei verbum, Mundi Opifex, Idaea boni, Mundi Archetypum, moderat or Diſtributor, Imago primi entis, rationalis Creaturae exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar, Paſtor, Sacerdos, vlna humens, Lux, Sol, coelumque candens, mentis germen Diuinae, verbum Lucidum, filius primogenitus, primi dei ſemper viuentis vmbra, vita, ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, virtus, candor lucis, character ſubſtantiae cius,</hi> and the like, which could not but flow from a heart diuinely toucht, and a tongue ſwolne with inſpiration, as <hi>Roſſelus</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:1978:20"/> tels vs in his <hi>Triſmegiſti Pimandrum,</hi> 1 booke, 107 <hi>page.</hi> For theſe and the like ſayings, ſome of the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue coniectured that <hi>Plato</hi> either read part of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſtory, or whilſt he trauelled in Egypt, had a taſte of ſacred truth, out of the ſayings of the Hebrewes by an <hi>Amanuenſis,</hi> or interpreter; For then many of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes (the Perſians reigning) wandered in Egypt.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> the Iew who flouriſhed in the time of the <hi>Machabees,</hi> writing to <hi>Ptolomy Philometora, King of Egypt,</hi> reports that the <hi>Pentateuch</hi> before the Empire of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, and the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie was Tranſlated out of Hebrew, into Greeke, part whereof came to the hands of <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Pythagoras;</hi> and he is after peremptory, that the <hi>Peripateticks</hi> out of the bookes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the writings of the Prophets drew the greateſt part of their Philoſophy, and it may ſeeme ſtrange what the Iewiſh Antiquary traditions of <hi>Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> (the moſt noble of that Sect) who in his firſt — <hi>De ſomno</hi> — brings in his Maſter <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> relating that he met with a certaine Iew, a reuerent and a wiſe man, with whom he had much conference concerning matters both naturall &amp; diuine, and receiued from him ſuch a hint and ſpecialty of choicer learning w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> did much improue him in his after knowledge, eſpecially in that of God, as <hi>Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus lib.</hi> 1. <hi>contra Appionem,</hi> &amp; <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his 11 <hi>de praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, Euangelica c.</hi> 6. <hi>Clement Alexandrin,</hi> 5. <hi>Stromaton</hi> —.</p>
            <p>And thus I haue at length (though with ſome blood and difficultie) trauerſed the opinions of the ancient, and ſhewed you the errours of primitiue Times in their fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſhapes. I haue opened the wiles and ſtratagems of the aduerſary, and how defeated by the chariots of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the horſemen thereof; what Bulwarkes and Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires the Fathers raiſed for propugning of Chriſts diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and how beſieged by curſed herefies, with what ſucceſſe, what ruine.</p>
            <p>Let vs now returne where we began, and place Chriſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1978:20"/> where we found him, before <hi>Abraham,</hi> before the world, where (me thinkes) he now ſtands like a well rooted tree in rough ſtorme, where though winds blow on him ſo furiouſly, that he is ſometimes forced to the earth (as if he were meerely humane) yet he bends againe, and nods towards heauen (to ſhew that hee is diuine, and but a plant taken thence grafted in our <hi>Eden</hi> here) where though toſt vp and downe with blaſts of Infidelity, yet when the enuy of their breath is ſpent (as we ſee a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Cedar after a tempeſt) he ſtands ſtrait, vn-rent, as if he ſcorned the ſhocke of his late churliſh encounter, and dared his bluſtring Aduerſary to a ſecond oppoſition.</p>
            <trailer>Gloria in excelfis Deo.</trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
